Hahn
The College of Saint Rose Archives
Hahn, Walter L., Collection
1924-1985
Hahn
The College of Saint Rose Archives
0.4 Linear feet (1 box)
The collection contains Clippings, photographs, drawings, postcards, correspondence, and scrapbook.
Arrangement note
The collection is organized into the following series:
Series 1: Newspaper Clippings, n.d. and 1942-1985
Series 2: Scrapbook from the College of Saint Rose, [1938?]-[1949?]
Series 3: Correspondence to Walter L. Hahn, 1925-1927, 1966, and n.d.
Series 4: Correspondence from Walter L. Hahn, 1954 and n.d.
Series 5: Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1924-1958
Series 6: Photographs and Drawings, 1945-1960s
Series 7: Public Relations Materials, 1961-1973 and n.d.
Series 8: Publications and Programs, 1944-1973
Conditions Governing Access note
There are no restrictions to this collection.
Biographical/Historical note
Walter Leo Hahn was the first professor at The College to be designated as a Professor Emeritus, named as such at the Honors Convocation on May 10, 1973. He taught Commerce (economics and business) at The College for 36 years, from 1937 to 1973. During the Alumni Testimonial Dinner in 1973, Mr. Hahn was granted honorary membership in the College of Saint Rose Alumni Association. He was also one of the first to be inducted into the Saint Rose Golden Knights Hall of Fame.
Professor Hahn also won the hearts of his students and colleagues by taking a leave of absence from teaching to serve in the United States Army in World War II. He joined the U.S. Army as a private, and left some forty-two months later as a Lieutenant Colonel. During his time in the service, he sent many letters and postcards to the faculty and students of Saint Rose.
Professor Hahn spoke and wrote extensively about the economic situation abroad. He was known as a world traveler, having visited Europe over 30 times, visited all 50 states, and, as of 1973, 141 countries.
"Professor, world traveler, athletic moderator, retired colonel, economist, bachelor, and rabble-rouser"; Walter Hahn stood out as a brilliant man, a dedicated educator, and a good friend to the College of Saint Rose community. He passed away on April 6, 1989.
Scope and Contents note
This collection stems from The College of Saint Rose’s Public Relations file on Professor Walter Hahn. A large part of the collection is various forms of press release and biographical information. There is however, one other element in the collection. The scrapbook and postcard collection reflect Professor Hahn’s love of stamps, love of travel, and his broad range of philanthropic and civic responsibilities.
Related Archival Materials note
Several textbooks written by Hahn are included in the Archives and Special Collections’ Early Textbook Collection.
- Newspaper Clippings, 1942, 1965-1985
  - Included is an article from the Rosaverian, June 1, 1942, that served as a farewell wish to Walter Hahn when he left the College of Saint Rose to serve in World War II. The majority of these clippings are from the Albany Times Union, the Knickerbocker News, and the Schenectady Gazette., 1942, 1965-1985 (Box 1)
- Scrapbook, 1938-1949
  - Black cardboard notebook (101/2" x 8") "College of Saint Rose" on cover in gold. The scrapbook contains articles related to Walter Hahn's hometown of Passaic New Jersey, articles about politics and World War II, and articles by Hahn himself. Also included are clippings regarding a trip with the Commerce Club to Washington D.C., articles related to speaking engagements, honors (NYU Alumni Club), guest lectures, an Albany Town Meeting (March 24, 1941) broadcast on local radio station WABY. Also contains Walter Hahn's Draft Board Card, dated February 27, 1942, with notations. There is a gap where Professor Hahn served in World War II. (42 months of service). The scrapbook ends with a Civil Service meeting announcement, and well wishes and articles relating to his return from service in WWII., 1938-1949 (Box 1)
- Correspondence to Walter L. Hahn, 1925-1927, 1966
  - From Dad and Mother, picture postcard, Havana Cuba, 02/05/1925 (Box 1)
  - From Dad and Mother, picture postcard, Kingston Jamaica, 02/09/1925 (Box 1)
  - From Mother and Dad, picture postcard, Panama Canal, 02/11/1925 (Box 1)
  - From Mother and Dad, picture postcard, Port-of-Spain, Trinidad, British West Indies, 02/16/1925 (Box 1)
  - From Mother and Dad, picture postcard, St. Thomas, Virgin Islands, 02/19/1925 (Box 1)
  - From Dad and Mother, picture postcard, San Juan, Puerto Rico, 02/20/1925 (Box 1)
  - From Mother and Dad, picture postcard, Crystal Cave, Bermuda, 02/25/1925 (Box 1)
  - From Ruth Chapman, picture postcard, Clarelly Quay, 08/06/1926 (Box 1)
  - From Connie and George, picture postcard, Hamilton, Ontario, 07/09/1927 (Box 1)
  - From L.M.L., picture postcard, Reims, France, 08/06/1927 (Box 1)
  - Envelope with commemorative postage, 6th International Philatelic Exhibition, Washington DC, 1966, 12/13/1966 (Box 1)
  - From Frances, picture postcard, St. Anne de Beaupré, Quebec, undated (Box 1)
  - From M.L. French, postcard, Munich, Germany, undated (Box 1)
  - From Milton French, postcard, Paris France, undated (Box 1)
  - From Hermann, picture postcard, Munich, Germany, undated (1937?) (Box 1)
  - From Ken and Shef, picture postcard, Stonoway, undated (Box 1)
  - From Lo, picture postcard, Cleveland, Ohio, undated (after 1933) (Box 1)
- Correspondence from Walter L. Hahn, 1954
  - To himself (for the stamps), picture postcard, Norway, 07/25/1954 (Box 1)
  - To Miss Marguerite Hahn, picture postcard, Norway, 07/25/1954 (Box 1)
  - To Miss Francis Gavin, picture postcard, Spain, undated (Box 1)
  - To Miss M.M. Hahn, picture postcard, Italy, undated (Box 1)
- Misecellaneous Correspondence, 1924-1958
  - To George Hahn from G. Egli, picture postcard, Zurich, Switzerland, 11/24/1924 (Box 1)
  - To Miss M. Hahn, from Mother and Dad, picture postcard, Havana Cuba, 02/05/1925 (Box 1)
  - To Miss M. Hahn, from Mother and Dad, picture postcard, Panama Canal, 02/11/1925 (Box 1)
  - To Mr. and Mrs. George Hahn, from Aunt Sarah, picture postcard, Strasbourg, 05/1926 (Box 1)
  - Envelope To Mme. Jacques Meyer from Mrs. Kuhn(?), Bois Rhin, Illustration on verso of the Tour of the battlefields, 06/23/1926 (Box 1)
  - To Mr. and Mrs. George Hahn, from Aunt Sarah, picture postcard, Paris, France, 06/29/1926 (Box 1)
  - To Mr. and Mrs. George Hahn, from Aunt Sarah, picture postcard, Brumath, 07/20/1926 (Box 1)
  - To Mr. And Mrs. George Hahn, from Paul and Mary Tarnoir (?), picture postcard, Checloslovokia, 08/04/1926 (Box 1)
  - To Mr. and Mrs. George Hahn, from Aunt Sara, picture postcard, Interlaken, Switzerland, 08/14/1926 (Box 1)
  - To Miss M. Hahn from Frances, picture postcard, Florence, Italy, 08/28/1926 (Box 1)
  - To George Hahn from Mrs. Barr, picture postcard, Reims, France, 09/24/1927 (Box 1)
  - To Mrs. Hahn from E. Millwood (?), picture postcard, Quebec, 08/11/1932 (Box 1)
  - To Miss Marguerite Hahn, from Hemoine, picture postcard, Panama, 03/10/1936 (Box 1)
  - To Miss Marguerite Hahn from Bill, picture postcard, Copenhagen, Denmark, 08/14/1936 (Box 1)
  - To Miss Marguerite Hahn, from Julia, picture postcard, Mexico, 07/09/1937 (Box 1)
  - To Mr. MilTon French, from Dr. Mayerhofer, postcard, Wurtzberg, Germany, 09/08/1937 (Box 1)
  - To MilTon L. French, from Dr. Mayerhofer, postcard, Ottingen/Bayern, Germany, 10/08/1937 (Box 1)
  - To Miss M. Hahn, envelope from Belgium with Nazi label, 1941 (Box 1)
  - To Miss Frances Gavin from M, picture postcard, Norway, 07/25/1954 (Box 1)
  - Commemorative Stamp and Envelope, Rural Municipality of Dauphin, ManiToba, Canada [2 copies], 07/11/1958 (Box 1)
  - Commemorative Envelope with Kennedy/Churchill Stamps, Paraguay, 11/05/1965 (Box 1)
  - To Miss Marguerite Marie Hahn, from Elizabeth Poussin (?), picture postcard, Belgium, undated (Box 1)
  - To Miss Loretta Hahn, holiday postcard, undated (Box 1)
- Photographs and Caricatures, 1945-1969
  - Caricature, Unsigned, Lisbon, 6 1/2” x 4”, 07/1956 (Box 1)
  - Photograph (press), 8x10 b/w, Walter Hahn receiving certificate regarding being the first professor emeritus at the College of Saint Rose, 05/10/1973 (Box 1)
  - Photograph, possibly for College of Saint Rose yearbook., marked with number 1317-2, 4 1/2" x 3”, undated (Box 1)
  - Photograph, portraits from CSR Development Office [3 copies], 1950-1969 (Box 1)
  - Photographs, reprints from originals, Nancy, France [3 copies], 02/1954 (Box 1)
- Public Relations Materials, 1961-1973
  - Letter to Ambrose P. Donovan, from Pat Dumas, re: biographical data sheet for Walter Hahn, 05/04/1961 (Box 1)
  - Note, re: on loan photograph of Professor Hahn with student, 03/02/1964 (Box 1)
  - Memo, to Mrs. Wood, from Barbara Hasso, re: Walter Hahn (biographical data), 09/27/1965 (Box 1)
  - Form for biographical data on Walter Hahn, 10/26/1965 (Box 1)
  - Memo, to Mr. Baker, from William Gonzalez, re: Professor Hahn’s retirement banquet, 05/02/1973 (Box 1)
  - Faculty File, Public Relations Office. Contains various versions of Walter Hahn’s biographical information, undated (Box 1)
  - Memo to Mrs. Merther from Barbara Hasso with letter and background material on Walter Hahn, with note attached from Professor Hahn, undated (Box 1)
  - Note and index card with handwritten biographical information, undated (Box 1)
  - Biographical information on paper (pencil), undated (Box 1)
  - Note (typed) to Bob from W. (Walter Hahn) re: press release for his election to the New York Department Reserve Officers Association, undated (Box 1)
  - Note (typed), from Walt to Barb re: updating his “background stuff”, undated (Box 1)
  - Press release re: Professor Hahn’s retirement, undated (Box 1)
  - Answer to mimeographed note about updating biographical information [Humorous response from Walter Hahn with signature], undated (Box 1)
  - Press release caption for photograph (see series 6, folder 6) “Walter Hahn gets certificate designating him 1st professor emeritus", undated (Box 1)
- Publications and Programs, 1944-1973
  - The Rosevarian [Commencement Issue] featuring on the back cover, a dedication of that issue to Walter Hahn, then in the U.S. Army serving in World War II, 05/29/1944 (Box 1)
  - Keynote, Volume 1, No. 3. Inauguration edition. Photographs of the Inauguration, including photographs with Walter Hahn, and a quote from Walter Hahn, 12/1966 (Box 1)
  - Delta Day: “Change and Continuity”. Walter Hahn, Speaker, 04/07/1973 (Box 1)
  - Program, A Tribute in Verse to Mr. Walter L. Hahn, Professor Emeritus, Business Department, The College of Saint Rose. Alumni Dinner, Hyatt House. [2 copies], 05/18/1973 (Box 1)
  - The Alumni Newsletter, with a large article about Walter Hahn, Vol. 4, No. 2, 06/1973 (Box 1)
  - Verbatim: Readings in English of the Holy Father’s Talks, with purchasing information, undated (Box 1)